SUMMARY

Software developer and interaction designer specializing in user interface design and development.

Over twenty five years of software design and development experience with a focus on user experience design; web application development using Django and Python; significant experience in JavaScript, Java, C and OCaml, interaction design, conceptual modeling, usability analysis and web accessibility evaluation.

EXPERIENCE

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER & INTERACTION DESIGNER, UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS — 2005-PRESENT

Lead designer and contributing developer of CKEditor plugins for the A11yFirst Project, including the Heading/Paragraph, Image, Link, Character Style and A11yFirst Help plugins, which are available on the CKEditor Add-ons website.

Lead designer and contributing developer of Alnspector WCAG, a Firefox browser add-on that provides web accessibility evaluation based on WCAG 2.0 requirements, available at addons.mozilla.org.

Lead developer and designer, in conjunction with Pixo, of the Accessibility Bookmarklets, web accessibility visualization tools compatible with all major browsers, available at accessibility-bookmarklets.org.

Lead designer and contributing developer of the Functional Accessibility Evaluator (FAE), a Django/Python web application that analyzes the accessibility of web resources.

INTERACTION DESIGN CONSULTANT, WEB UI, CHICAGO, IL - 1999-2005

As principal of Web UI, Inc., provided software design and development services with an emphasis on human-computer interaction design and web application development for Fortune 500 clients, including ABN AMRO, Accenture, Allstate Insurance, DeVry University, Fidelity Investments, HOLT Value Associates and Illinois Institute of Technology.

USER INTERFACE DESIGNER & DEVELOPER, FIDELITY INVESTMENTS, MARLBORO, MA — 1997-1999

Served as principal interaction designer in the redesign of NetBenefits, a web application providing retirement savings account access to over one million customers. Improved the user experience through contextual inquiry, task flow analysis and usability testing.

According to an article published in the New York Times, in the year following the deployment of the new design, the number of retirement savings account customer service calls was reduced by 50 percent compared to the previous year.

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER & USER INTERFACE DESIGNER, BGS SYSTEMS, WALTHAM, MA — 1991-1997

Responsible for X Window/Motif user interface design and C/C++ development of capacity planning and performance analysis products on Unix and VMS platforms. Investigated the feasibility of using Java for migrating to platform-independent user interface development.

EDUCATION

University of Massachusetts Boston — BA in Computer Science with Distinction, Summa Cum Laude, 1991 Berklee College of Music, Boston, MA — Jazz Composition & Arranging major, 1981–1984

SKILLS

Interaction design: requirements gathering and analysis; development of conceptual models, personas, scenarios, essential use cases, user role- and task-models; creation of wireframes using OmniGraffle and Visio.

User interface development: JavaScript (ES6), Node.js, npm, Babel, webpack, HTML5, CSS, DOM, XUL (XML User Interface Language for Firefox extensions), Diango, Python, Java, SQL, C/C++, X Window/Motif, iOS, Cocoa Touch, Objective-C.

Usability analysis and testing: creation of interactive prototypes, task lists and surveys for testing; facilitation of discount and lab-based usability testing; quantitative and qualitative analysis of test results.

User research & information architecture: field observations, contextual interviews, user role- and task-modeling workshops, card sorting exercises, paper prototyping.

CONTACT INFO

https://www.linkedin.com/in/nhoyt — Additional details available upon request